Guide to the Islamic and Arabian Development Studies records, 1977-2000
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Islamic and Arabian Development Studies records 1977-2000
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Islamic and Arabian Development Studies.
1.6 Linear Feet 1,250 Items
The program was established in 1977 with funding from the Greater Charlotte Foundation. The program became fully operational in the 1978-1979 academic year under the directorship of Ralph Braibanti. Studies focused primarily on the Arabian Peninsula and its social, economic, and political developments, and on the resurgence of Islam, with some attention also paid to Arabic archaeology, art, language, law and literature.
Collection contains primarily reports and other printed materials, along with conference programs, and a small amount of the Director's correspondence. Materials range in date from 1976-2000.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Islamic and Arabian Development Studies records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980, 1989, 1991, 2000.
Biographical Note
The program was established in 1977 with funding from the Greater Charlotte Foundation. Later on, support was obtained from the government of Saudi Arabia, the Exxon Corporation, and other private and public bodies. The program became fully operational in the 1978-1979 academic year under the directorship of Ralph Braibanti. Studies focused primarily on the Arabian Peninsula and its social, economic, and political developments, and on the resurgence of Islam, with some attention also paid to Arabic archaeology, art, language, law and literature. Several conferences and trips were sponsored, and the program played a role in the visit of Queen Noor of Jordan to Duke in 1985. Funding for the program expired in August 1989, which was also the date of Dr. Braibanti's retirement from active teaching.
Collection Overview
Collection contains primarily reports and other printed materials, along with conference programs, and a small amount of the Director's correspondence. Director's correspondence is closed until August 2014 by donor's request. Includes annual and triennial reports of the program, 1977-1988, covering faculty activities, curriculum development, lectures, travel reports, and other aspects of the program; a catalog of the Joseph J. Malone Collection on Arabian Affairs; reprints; newspaper clippings; and course syllabi and readings. Materials range in date from 1976-2000.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American Institute of Pakistan Studies.
Arab countries -- Study and teaching.
Braibanti, Ralph J. D.
Civilization, Arab -- Study and teaching.
Civilization, Islamic -- Study and teaching.
Duke University. Islamic and Arabian Development Studies.
Islamic countries -- Study and teaching.
Malone, Joseph J.--Archives -- Catalogs.
Related Material
Louis Dupree papers, 1943-1989.
University Archives, Duke University.
Report of the ... year [serial].
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - IADS Three-Year Report, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - IADS Three-Year Report and supplement, 1981-1984
  - IADS Activities Report, 1984-1985
  - IADS Activities Report, 1985-1988
  - IADS Summary of Activities Report, 1977-1988
  - IADS Annual and Triennial Reports, 1977-1988 c.1
  - IADS Annual and Triennial Reports, 1977-1988 c.2
  - IADS: PS148 Political Development in the Arabian Peninsula. Syllabus, 1980
  - IADS: Summer Program: Syllabus and Readings, 1981
  - IADS: Seminar: The Recovery of Islamic Identity in Global Perspective, 1980
  - Director - Correspondence, 1976-1986 (2 folders) [RESTRICTED] (Box 2)
  - The Nomination of Dr. Ralph Braibanti… for the King Faisal International Prize in Islamic Studies, 1987
  - Braibanti, Ralph. Position Paper #1: "The Nature and Structure of the Islamic World" (1995)
  - Reprints: Saudi Arabia: A Developmental Perspective, 1979 (2 copies); The Recovery of Islamic Identity in Global Perspective, 1979
  - Joseph J. Malone Collection on Arabian Affairs catalog American Institute of Pakistan Studies, Directory of Publications and Misc. Materials (1987-1988)
  - National Council on U.S. Arab Relations: Occasional Papers #7
  - IADS "International Conferences on Saudi Arabian Development," 1979, 1982
  - IADS: Guestbook, 1982-1989
  - Newsletters, misc. printed matter
  - Misc. News articles
  - Printed matter - Braidanti, Ralph - articles, 1999-2000